Guide to the William J. Baumol Papers, 1928-2013 and undated RL.00092
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William J. Baumol Papers
1928-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Baumol, William J.
RL.00092
130 Linear Feet
5.74 Gigabytes
William J. Baumol (1922-2017) was an economist and worked as a professor of economics at Princeton University and New York University. This collection consists of his correspondence, research, writings, his collaborations and professional affiliations, and his work as a painter and sculptor.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The papers of William J. Baumol, Princeton and New York University economist, were received as a gift to the Rubenstein Library between 1995 and 2020.
Biographical Note
Biographical Note
1922, February 26 Born in New York, N.Y.
1936-1938 Attended first formal art classes sponsored by the Works Progress Administration.
1942 BSS, College of the City of New York; organized extracurricular classes on microeconomics.
1942-1943 and 1946 Junior Economist, U.S. Department of Agriculture.
1943-1945 Served in U.S. Army, stationed in France.
1946-1949 London School of Economics; Graduate Student and Assistant Lecturer in American Economy and Economic Dynamics. (Lecture notes for the latter formed the basis for his first published book, Economic Dynamics, 1951, 1959, 1970).
1949 Completed University of London Ph. D. thesis, later published as Welfare Economics and the Theory of the State, 1952, 1965. Ph.D. examiners were Marcus Flemming and Lord Lionel Robbins.
1949-1953 Associate Professor of Economics, Princeton University.
1954-1992 Professor of Economics, Princeton University.
1959 Publication of Business Behavior, Value and Growth (second edition 1966).
1961 Publication of Economic Theory and Operations Analysis (later editions in 1965, 1972, 1976).
1962-1970 Chairman, Committee on the Economic Status of the Profession, American Association of University Professors.
1966 Publication with W.G. Bowen of Performing Arts: The Economic Dilemma.
1967-1975 Past Chairman and member, Economic Policy Council, State of New Jersey.
1968-1970 Vice-President, American Association of University Professors.
1971-current Professor of Economics and Director, C.V. Starr Center for Applied Economics, New York University.
1975 Publication with W.E. Oates of The Theory of Environmental Policy, (second edition 1988).
1978 President, Eastern Economics Association.
1978-1979 President, Association of Environmental and Resource Economists.
1979 Publication with A.S. Blinder of the first edition of introductory textbook, Economics: Principles and Policies. Later editions in 1982, 1985, 1987, 1991, 1994, and 1998.
1981 President, American Economics Association.
1982 Publication with J.C. Panzar and R.D. Willig of Contestable Markets and the Theory of Industry Structure (second edition 1982).
1984 Editor with wife, Hilda Baumol, of Inflation and the Performing Arts.
1986 Publication of Superfairness: Applications and Theory.
1992-2017 Senior Research Economist and Professor Emeritus of Economics, Princeton University.
May 4, 2017 Died in New York, NY
Collection Overview
The William Baumol papers document his career as an economist and artist. The collection provides an overview of his professional activities, including his research on the cost disease, unbalanced growth, productivity growth, entrepreneurship, increasing returns and international trade, anti-trust policy, contestable markets, market structure, macroeconomic theory, and interest rate and monetary theory, among other topics. Baumol's research and writings on the economics of the arts, undertaken and co-authored with his wife Hilda, are included in the collection.
The collection also documents his collaboration and communication with prominent economists such as Maurice Allais, Gary Becker, Alan Blinder, George Dantzig, Robert Dorfman, Milton Friedman, John Kenneth Galbraith, Ralph Gomory, Frank Hahn, Roy Harrod, John Hicks, Ursula Hicks, Samuel Hollander, Nicholas Kaldor, Harold Kuhn, Abba Lerner, Jacob Marschak, Don Patinkin, Lionel Robbins, Joan Robinson, Paul Samuelson, Ralph Turvey, Jacob Viner, and Edward Wolff, among others. Of note is Baumol's longtime collaboration with, and extensive support received from, Sue Anne Batey Blackman.
Along with his scholarship and writings, the collection documents Baumol's leadership roles at the Berkley Center for Entrepreneurship and Innovation and the C.V. Starr Center for Applied Economics at New York University, as well as his extensive expert witness and consulting activities for the Federal Communications Commission, Federal Trade Commission, the Interstate Commerce Commission, the Joint Economic Committee, and the Senate Judiciary Committee, among others. Baumol's consulting was often done through the companies Alderson and Sessions, Mathematica, and Consultants in Industry Economics. His notable expert witness testimonies revolved around regulation in telecommunications (particularly the ATT monopoly), airline ticket prices and sales practices, pricing of railroad freight shipping, and other topics.
Materials from Baumol's teaching at Princeton and New York University, departmental, and committee work are included in the collection. The collection also contains samples of Baumol's artwork, including sketches and paintings.
Arrangement note
PROCESSING NOTE: The materials received by Duke University arrived from Professor Baumol's offices at Princeton, New York University, and from his private residence. These were treated as one single accession and the materials from all three shipments have been consolidated. Hence, while the original organization has been mostly preserved at the folder level, at the box level this is not the case. Wherever possible the original folder labels were used in organizing the collection. Notable exceptions to this are the material in the Legal Testimony subseries and materials on the performing arts, government projects, and industry consulting as the bulk of this material was received loose. It was not possible to map every digital file recovered from floppy disks to particular projects, writings, or other files. In these cases generic classifiations were made in the arrangement.
Conditions Governing Access note
[Original audiovisual materials and original electronic media are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
Conditions Governing Access
Access restricted; Accession 2020-0078 requires additional arrangement, description, and/or screening. Contact research services for more information.
Antitrust investigations-United States; Labor economics; Statics and dynamics (Social sciences); Industrial productivity; Machine-readable records; Performing Arts -- Finance; Performing Arts -- United States -- Finance; Audiotapes; Environmental policy -- Economic aspects; Environmental economics; Public utilities-United States-Law and legislation; Telephone companies-Rates; Education -- Finance; Electric utilities -- Rates; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; Distributive justice; Entrepreneurship; Monetary policy; Welfare economics; Economics, Mathematical; Railroad companies -- Rates; Viner, Jacob, 1892-1970; United States. Interstate Commerce Commission; United States. Federal Energy Regulatory Commission; United States. Federal Communications Commission; Turvey, Ralph; Robertson, Dennis Holme, Sir, 1890-1963; Leibenstein, Harvey; Meade, J. E. (James Edward), 1907-; Friedman, Milton, 1912-2006; Samuelson, Paul A. (Paul Anthony), 1915-2009; Patinkin, Don; Robbins, Lionel Robbins, Baron, 1898-1984; Hahn, Frank; Hayek, Friedrich A. von (Friedrich August), 1899-; Hicks, John, 1904-1989; Kaldor, Nicholas, 1908-1986; Becker, Gary S. (Gary Stanley), 1930-2014; Dorfman, Robert; Graaff, J. de V.; Baumol, Hilda, 1923-; Baumol, William J.
- Correspondence, 1943-2012 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Contains chronological and name files on Baumol's correspondence with various individuals. Correspondence from the earlier decades of Baumol's career was maintained in chronological folders, while name folders were reserved for only some correspondents. Correspondence with notable individuals has been organized into name folders where appropriate, however, correspondence with some notable individuals remains in chronological folders to maintain coherence where conversations took place between multiple individuals. Correspondents of note include: Maurice Allais, Gary Becker, George Dantzig, Robert Dorfman, Milton Friedman, John Kenneth Galbraith, Ralph Gomory, Frank Hahn, Roy Harrod, John Hicks, Ursula Hicks, Samuel Hollander, Nicholas Kaldor, Harold Kuhn, Abba Lerner, Jacob Marschak, Don Patinkin, Lionel Robbins, Joan Robinson, Paul Samuelson, Ralph Turvey, Jacob Viner, and Edward Wolff.
  Much of Baumol's correspondence for specific research projects was originally organized with his files for the published work or with the relevant research materials. To maintain the original organization, additional correspondence of this kind can be found in the Writings and Research and Notes series.
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1943-2012; 1
    Contains correspondence arranged by date.
    - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 60)
      Includes correspondence about graduate studies at the London School of Economics
    - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1948-1953 (Box 84)
      Includes correspondence with Friedrich Lutz, Ralph Turvey, and J. van de Graff
    - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 60)
      Includes correspondence with Tibor Scitovsky sharing current work
    - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 60)
      Includes correspondence with Ralph Turvey
    - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 60)
      Includes routine correspondence with Maurice Allais, James Meade, Ralph Turvey, and Robert Strotz
    - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 60)
      Includes routine correspondence with Maurice Allais
    - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 60)
      Includes routine correspondence with Maurice Allais and Ralph Turvey
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 60)
      Includes brief correspondence with John Kenneth Galbraith
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 60)
      Includes brief correspondence with Nicholas Kaldor and Joan Robinson
    - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1964; 4 folders (Box 60)
      Includes brief correspondence with Jack Hirshleifer, James Tobin, and Fritz Machlup
    - Correspondence, 1965; 2 folders (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1966; 4 folders (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1967; 3 folders (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1968; 3 folders (Box 60)
      Includes brief correspondence with Abba Lerner
    - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1971; 2 folders (Box 60)
    - Correspondence, 1971; 2 folders (Box 61)
    - Correspondence, 1972; 2 folders (Box 61)
    - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 61)
    - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 61)
    - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 61)
    - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 61)
      Includes brief correspondence with George Dantzig
    - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 61)
      Includes brief correspondence with Harold Kuhn, Karl Shell, and Hugo Sonnenschein
    - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 61)
    - Correspondence, 1981; 2 folders (Box 61)
    - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 61)
    - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 61)
    - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 61)
    - Correspondence, 1985; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1986; 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1987; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1987; 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1988; 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1989; 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1990; 9 folders (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1990-1991; 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1998 (Box 42)
    - Correspondence, 1992; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1993; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1994-1995; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 2001 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 2002 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 2003 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 2004 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 2005-2006; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 2007 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 2008 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 2009 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 2010 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 2011 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, 2012 (Box 9)
    - Routine correspondence, 1980-1988; 112 files (post script and unidentified formats); less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0020)
    - Routine correspondence, 1989-1990; 10 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0037)
    - Routine correspondence, 1990; 4 unidentified files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0117)
    - Routine correspondence, 1994; 3 document files (WordPerfect format); less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL3-0002)
  - Name and Subject Correspondence, 1948-2010 and undated; 2
    Contains correspondence arranged alphabetically by name and subject.
    - American Economic Review, 1975-1984 (Box 9)
    - Areeda-Turner, 1978-1984 (Box 9)
      Includes correspondence with Phillip Areeda and Donald Turner on predatory pricing
    - Becker, Gary, 1951-1979 (Box 9)
      Includes correspondence about writing together
    - Causes, 1980-2006; 3 folders (Box 9)
      Includes correspondence about causes Baumol supported, such as human rights, tax policy, government funding for research, and political prisoners
    - Clinton, 1992-1993 (Box 9)
      Includes letters to Hillary Clinton expressing interest in health care legislation
    - Cost Disease, 1993-1995 (Box 9)
      Includes correspondence about Baumol's book Cost Disease
    - Cranks, 1964-1995 (Box 9)
      Includes non-academic correspondence from untrustworthy sources
    - Dorfman, Robert, 1975-1978 (Box 9)
      Includes correspondence about Marxian economics and other topics
    - Duke University, 1978-2005 (Box 9)
      Includes correspondence coordinating Baumol's papers at the Rubenstein Library
    - Entrepreneurship, 1984-1987; 7 unidentified files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0097)
    - Entrepreneurship and Education, 2004 (Box 9)
    - Entrepreneurship and other routine matters, 1980; 27 text files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-FL5-0008)
      Includes correspondence on entrepreneurship, publication with journals, and other routine matters.
    - Environmental Economics, 1973-1974 (Box 9)
      Includes correspondence discussing topics in environmental economics
    - Friedman, Milton, 1949-1951 (Box 9)
      Includes routine correspondence
    - Gomory, Ralph, 2010 (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence about joint work
      - American Standard of Living Sustainable and One Man's Views of Unrestricted Free Trade, Not Fair Trade, 2007; 6 audiovisual files; approximately 4 GB. (Digital-materials RL00092-SET-0001, Disk RL00092-OP-0007)
        Includes videos of talks hosted by Nelson Hoffman.
    - Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Inc., 1975-1987 (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence about publications
    - Harrod, Roy F., 1948-1951 (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence about publications and economic dynamics
    - Hicks, John R., 1948; 1973 (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence about convergence of equilibrium in reference to work by Richard Kahn and Paul Samuelson
    - Hollander, Samuel, 1964-1986 (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence about the history of economic ideas, particularly figures like Ricardo and Marx
    - Intermountain Economic Review, 1977 (Box 62)
    - Journal of Economic Education, 1983-1990 (Box 62)
    - Journal of Economic Literature, 1975 (Box 62)
    - Journal of Environmental Economics and Management, 1976 (Box 62)
    - Kluwer Academic Publishers, 1996 (Box 62)
    - Kyklos, 1976-1986 (Box 62)
    - London School of Economics, 1974-1994 (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence about the Lionel Robbins fund and other routine correspondence
    - Marschak, Jacob, 1952 (Box 62)
    - Marxian Economics, 1973-1983; 3 folders (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence with Paul Samuelson, Robert Dorfman, Samuel Hollander, Anwar Shaikh, and others about topics in Marxian economics
    - Mateja, Mary, 1984-1985 (Box 62)
    - McMeakin, Gordon, 2002-2003 (Box 62)
    - New York Times, 1996 (Box 62)
    - Performing Arts Correspondence, 1973-1994; 2 folders (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence about pricing and financing of performing arts, among other related topics
    - Productivity, 1984-1995; 3 folders (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence about various themes in productivity growth
    - Professional Theory, etc., 1969-1970 (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence about professional conduct and academic personnel policies
    - Publishers, 1960-1977 (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence with various academic publishers
    - Quarterly Journal of Economics, 1975-1984 (Box 62)
    - Robbins, Lionel, 1950-1966 (Box 62)
    - Samuelson, Paul, 1949-2005 (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence about exchanging papers and other routine correspondence
    - Shackle, George L.S., 1949-1954 (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence about exchanging papers
    - Stigler, George, 1951-1959 (Box 62)
    - Tinbergen, Jan, 1953-1955 (Box 62)
    - Undated (Box 62)
    - Viner, Jacob, 1954-1968 (Box 62)
    - Ratner, Sidney, 1981-1995; 4 folders (Box 36)
      Includes correspondence about Ratner's memoirs and autobiographical material for the Oral History Research Office at Columbia University
    - Hahn, Frank, 1950-1959 (Box 83)
      Includes correspondence about the wage share of national income, the Ricardo effect, general equilibrium and money, dynamics models, other research, and routine matters
    - Patinkin, Don, 1953-1961 (Box 83)
      Includes correspondence about dynamics models, Say's Law, Keynesian macroeconomics, theories of the interest rate, exchanging articles, and other routine matters
    - Edward Elgar, 1988-1989 (Box 42)
      Includes correspondence related to working with the publisher
    - Friedman, Milton, 1993 (Box 42)
      Includes correspondence related to Friedman's comment on an article by Baumol and Edward Wolff
    - Gomory, Ralph, 1992 (Box 42)
      Includes correspondence related to sharing work
    - Journal of Economic Literature, 1981-1990 (Box 42)
      Includes correspondence with the journal
    - Journal of Law and Economics, 1984-1986 (Box 42)
    - Permissions to Publish, 1972-1984 (Box 42)
      Includes correspondence related to granting permissions to republish materials
    - Ratner, Sidney, 1981-1995; 3 folders (Box 42)
      Includes correspondence related to Ratner's contribution to the Oral History Research Office at Columbia University
    - Ratner, Sidney, 1981 (Box 85)
    - Reprint Requests, 1985-1988; 2 folders (Box 85)
    - Wolff, Edward, undated (Box 85)
      Includes undated hand-written correspondence with Edward Wolff
    - Schleifer, Andrei, 1991 (Box 85)
      Includes Schleifer's comment on Baumol's book about Entrepreneurship
    - Tullock, Gordon, 1974-1985 (Box 85)
      Includes brief correspondence about Baumol's writing on rent seeking and Tullock's writing on the economics of theater in London
- Professional Service, 1942-2010 and undated
  This series includes files on Baumol's professional activities. These include: conference and workshop presentations and organization; files related to service with professional organizations and research institutes; and files from consulting and legal testimony.
  - Conferences, Consulting, and Organizations, 1942-2010 and undated; 1
    This subseries includes files on Baumol's activities related to conferences (presenting research and sometimes organizing conferences or conference sessions), his consulting activities outside of official legal testimonies, and his involvement with various professional and research organizations.
    - aDvANCE Project, 2004 (Box 59)
      Includes files related to service on board
    - American Economic Association (AEA): Adam Smith Session, 1977 (Box 62)
      Includes materials for conference panel
    - AEA: Association Environment Session, 1976 (Box 62)
      Includes materials for conference session
    - AEA: China Exchange Committee, 1980 (Box 62)
      Includes correspondence related to committee activities
    - AEA: Committee on Political Discrimination, 1977-1978 (Box 62)
      Includes materials for committee work on cases of political discrimination in the economics profession
    - AEA: Encyclopedia Committee, 1980 (Box 62)
      Includes materials for committee work on proposed encyclopedia
    - AEA: Meetings, 1976-1984; 3 folders (Box 62)
      Includes materials and correspondence related to conference sessions
    - AEA: Nominating Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 62)
      Includes materials from service on nominating committee
    - AEA: Presidential Address, 1981-1982 (Box 62)
      Includes materials for presidential address as well as notes and comments
    - AEA: Session on Entrepreneurship, Innovation, and Growth, 2006 (Box 40)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1982-1983 (Box 62)
    - American Association of University Professors, 1965 (Box 62)
    - American Hospital: What Does the Future Hold, 2003 (Box 63)
      Includes materials for conference presentation
    - American Philosophical Society, 1992-2010; 2 folders (Box 63)
      Includes correspondence about society business
    - American Stock Exchange, 1977 (Box 63)
      Includes materials related to Baumol's service on the nominating committee
    - American Symphony Orchestra League, 1980 (Box 18)
      Includes correspondence and other files related to a conference
    - Association of College, University, and Community Arts Administrators (ACUCAA), 1980-1985; 2 folders (Box 18)
      Includes files related to membership and conference presentation
    - Association of American Railroads, 1963 (Box 63)
      Includes materials from service on economists panel reviewing costs and pricing for railroad service
    - Association of Environmental and Resource Economists, 1977-1984; 2 folders (Box 63)
      Includes materials related to service on the association board
    - Baumol and Malkiel - Autodesk, 2002-2003 (Box 63)
      Includes materials for report to Autodesk on factors in management decisions
    - Berkley Center, 2006-2009; 4 folders (Box 63)
      Includes files for grant proposals and funding of center for entrepreneurial studies
    - Canadian Railroads, 1976 (Box 15)
      Includes consulting report for Canadian Pacific Railroad
    - Carpenter Steel Company, 1957 (Box 15)
      Includes draft inventory study
    - Chicago Talks, undated (Box 63)
      Includes notes for multiple presentations on Lionel Robbins, cost disease, and income distribution and growth
    - Conference Board: Committee for Economic Development, 1982; 2 folders (Box 15)
      Includes materials related to committee service